<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The safety of Jerusalem exprest in a sermon to the Right Honourable the Lord Mayor, with the Aldermen and Common-Councill of London in the parish-church of Laurence Jury, on Tuesday the XXIV of March, MDCLVI, being the day of their solemne thanks-giving for the health and safety of the city, in its preservation from pestilence, fire, and other calamities / by Thomas Horton ...</title>
            <author>Horton, Thomas, d. 1673.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1657</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 93 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44568</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2880</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8361</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13530825</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13530825</idno>
            <idno type="VID">99989</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A44568)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 99989)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 790:33)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The safety of Jerusalem exprest in a sermon to the Right Honourable the Lord Mayor, with the Aldermen and Common-Councill of London in the parish-church of Laurence Jury, on Tuesday the XXIV of March, MDCLVI, being the day of their solemne thanks-giving for the health and safety of the city, in its preservation from pestilence, fire, and other calamities / by Thomas Horton ...</title>
                  <author>Horton, Thomas, d. 1673.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 43, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Clarke ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Isaiah XXXVII, 35 --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:99989:1"/>
            <p>THE SAFETY OF JERUSALEM, EXPREST In a SERMON to the Right Honourable the Lord Mayor, with the Aldermen, and Common-Councill of LONDON.</p>
            <p>In the Pariſh-Church of <hi>Laurence Jury.</hi> On Tueſday the XXIV of <hi>March,</hi> MDCLVI. Being, the day of Their Solemne THANKS-GIVING, For the Health and Safety of the City, In its Preſervation from <hi>Peſtilence, Fire,</hi> and other <hi>Calamities.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By THOMAS HORTON, D. D.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ESAY. 68.18.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Thou ſhalt call thy Walls SALVA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TION, and thy Gates PRAISE.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>REVEL. 21.26.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>They ſhall bring the GLORY and HONO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R of the Nation into it.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>John Clarke</hi> at <hi>Mercers-Chappell</hi> in <hi>Cheap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide,</hi> neere the great <hi>Conduit,</hi> 1657.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:99989:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:99989:2"/>
            <head>The Epiſtle Dedicatory.</head>
            <head type="sub">TO THE RIGHT HONOURABLE Sir ROBERT TICHBOURN, Knight Lord Mayor, with the Right Worſhipfull the Aldermen, And the reſt of the Common-Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cill of the Famous City of <hi>LONDON.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <hi>RIGHT HONOURABLE,</hi> &amp;c.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
               </hi> WAS in good hope when this <hi>Sermon</hi> was once preached, that I had no further worke about it, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it were onely to work it upon my <hi>owne</hi> heart, and to pray for a Bleſſing upon it, in the hearts of thoſe that <hi>heard</hi> it. Whereas now ſince ſome weekes after, I received an Order from <hi>your Court,</hi> for the commending it to <hi>publique view;</hi> But it took me at ſuch a time, when I was very little at leaſure for it; From whence it is now come forth both <hi>too ſoone</hi> and <hi>too late.</hi> Too ſoone in regard of <hi>it ſelfe,</hi> which deſerves not this Publication,
<pb facs="tcp:99989:3"/>Too late in regard of the <hi>Occaſion,</hi> which is now ſo long time paſt as that I feare it is almoſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten in the minds of many men, although it be ſuch as hath cauſe to be alwayes remembred.</p>
            <p>I doe ſo much the willinglyer cloſe with the impartment of this <hi>Diſcourſe,</hi> as it may ſerve to revive the <hi>memory</hi> of that mercy, which is the <hi>ſubject</hi> of it; and may conferre ſomething to the renewall of our <hi>Thankfulneſſe</hi> for it. The more and greater <hi>Bleſſings</hi> we doe profeſſe to have received from God, the more and greater doe we conſequently declare our <hi>Ingagements</hi> to be to Him which are to run out in anſwerable Fruitfulneſſe and Activity for Him. That this may be the Generall <hi>Improvement</hi> of the mercy, which is here proclaim'd, is the hearty wiſh and Prayer of</p>
            <signed>Your Honour's moſt humble Servant for the Truth's ſake, THOMAS HORTON.</signed>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:99989:3"/>
            <head>THE SAFETY <hi>OF</hi> JERUSALEM.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ESAY. XXXVII. VER. XXXV.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>For I will defend this City to ſave it for mine owne ſake, and for my ſervant Davids ſake.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is the great care, and tenderneſſe of God to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his Church and people, not only to keep them from <hi>Evill,</hi> but like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe from the <hi>Feare</hi> of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, which ſometimes is a great deale more then the <hi>Evill it ſelfe;</hi> The <hi>former,</hi> to provide for their <hi>ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty;</hi> the <hi>latter</hi> to provide for their <hi>ſecurity,</hi> and tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillity of mind. Look, as on the one ſide the <hi>Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,</hi> he does not only <hi>perſecute,</hi> but <hi>threaten,</hi> nor he does not only <hi>project</hi> and deſigne miſchief, but often
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:99989:4"/>braggs, and <hi>boaſts</hi> of it aforehand thereby to daunt the courage and to allay the Spirits of the people of God: So on the other ſide <hi>God</hi> himſelfe, he does not only <hi>protect,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Cohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence.</note> but <hi>comfort,</hi> nor he does not only <hi>purpoſe</hi> and intend preſervation, but gives ſome hints and <hi>predictions</hi> of it, that ſo thereby he may the better ſtrengthen and incourage his peoples hearts. This we may obſerve him to doe in the drift of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Scripture, which we have now in hand. <hi>Sena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherib</hi> the King of <hi>Aſſyria</hi> had in the foregoing chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and this ſent his ſervant <hi>Rebſhakeh</hi> with an inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and reviling meſſage to <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> and the reſt of <hi>Judah</hi> threatning them what great matters he would doe againſt them, and their City; This <hi>Hezekiah</hi> and his people were very much affrighted, at, and affected with, and accordingly ſpread their caſe and condition before the Lord. Now the Lord hereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on undertakes the ſatisfying, and comforting of them; tells them what ever threats their enemy might make againſt them, he ſhould not once come neer unto them, nor enter amongſt them, and in the Verſe which I have now read unto you gives an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count and reaſon of it whence it ſhould be ſo; not from any change in the enemy, as if his mind were bettered towards them, but rather from Gods own conſtancy of affection to them, and care for them, <hi>For I will defend this City to ſave it for mine own ſake</hi> &amp;c. This is the <hi>Cohaerence</hi> of the words.</p>
            <p>The Text (as you ſee) points at the ſafety and preſervation of a <hi>City,</hi> the City of <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> and ſo very well ſutes with the occaſion of our coming to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether at this time, which is the ſafety and preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our <hi>own,</hi> the City of <hi>LONDON:</hi> And though not every way juſt in the ſame Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:99989:4"/>of deliverance, yet perhaps (if we conſider all) not altogether different from them, and beſides with ſome what more, joyned, and ſuper-added un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, not onely from the ſword of the <hi>Enemy,</hi> but alſo from the ſword of the <hi>Angell,</hi> nor onely from the combuſtions of <hi>warr,</hi> but from the fires of <hi>Peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Text it ſelfe there are two generall parts obſervable, Firſt, the <hi>Mercy ſignified,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Diviſion.</note> And Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the <hi>Ground,</hi> or Motive for the beſtowing of it: The Mercy ſignified, that we have in theſe words; <hi>For I will defend this City to ſave it.</hi> The ground or Motive of it, in theſe; <hi>For my owne ſake, and for my ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant Davids ſake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We begin with the firſt generall, <hi>viz.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The <hi>firſt Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erall.</hi>
               </note> The mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy ſignified, wherein two Particulars more. Firſt, The <hi>Specification.</hi> And ſecondly, The <hi>Amplificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> The Specification, or mercy it ſelfe, which is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt, <hi>I will defend this City.</hi> The Amplification or extent of the mercy, <hi>To ſave it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, To ſpeak of the former, <hi>viz.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Specifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the mercy.</note> The <hi>Specifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of the mercy, or the mercy it ſelfe, which is here ſignified; it is Divine protection, and defence, I will defend this City, <hi>1?</hi> Who is that? Namely, God himſelfe, who here ſends this meſſage by his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, it is he that takes this buſineſſe of defence and protection upon him, one who was able enough to doe it, and to goe through with it. And <hi>this City</hi> which was that? Namely, <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> the City of God, where his name and worſhip was celebrated; That's the City which is here promiſed the benefit of Gods defence and preſervation of it; ſo that there are two things here now conſiderable. The <hi>Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,</hi> and the <hi>Defendant,</hi> The <hi>Defended,</hi> that's this Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; The <hi>Defendant</hi> that's the <hi>God of Iſraell,</hi> Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:99989:5"/>
            <p>For the Firſt,<note place="margin">The Defended.</note> The place defended, it was <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> the City of God; This was that which was the object of this defence, and which this protection ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended unto, which accordingly ſhewes unto us the ſtate and condition of the Church in all ſucceding ages and generations; This promiſe it is not to be limited or reſtrained to this preſent time, or occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whereupon it was made, but in the force and effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy of it, does reach to all periods of time through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the World, <hi>And is written even for our conſolation, upon whom the ends of the world are come, that we through patience and comfort of the Scriptures might have hope: Rom.</hi> 15.4. and 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10, 11. The point before us is this; That the <hi>Church</hi> and people of God, they are under a ſpeciall ſafeguard and protection, for the ſecurity and defence of them. This City, though it be a word of <hi>mixture,</hi> and ſo does ſeeme to take in all with it, who were occaſionally involved in the mercy, yet it does principally, and more particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly referr to the <hi>Church</hi> and true Believers, who were the better part of it. The <hi>Church</hi> it is not without a fence, it is a <hi>Garden encloſed;</hi> and thoſe places where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it reſides, they doe partake of ſpeciall cuſtody, and preſervation, in reference to it. <hi>This City</hi> it ſhall be defended; Thus <hi>Zechar.</hi> 2.4, 5. <hi>Jeruſalem ſhall be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habited as Townes without walls, for the multitude of men and cattell therein, For I (ſaith the Lord) will be unto her a wall of fire round about, and will be the glory in the midſt of her.</hi> So Zechar. 12.8. <hi>In that day ſhall the Lord defend the Inhabitants of Jeruſalem, and he that is feeble among them at that day ſhall be as</hi> David, <hi>and the houſe of</hi> David <hi>ſhall be as God, as the Angell of the Lord before him.</hi> So Iſa. 31.5. <hi>As birds flying, ſo will the Lord of Hoſts defend</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>defending alſo he will
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:99989:5"/>deliver it, and paſſing over he will preſerve it,</hi> As <hi>Birds flying,</hi> that is with great deale of <hi>tenderneſſe.</hi> Birds we know, they are very carefull of their young ones for the preſerving of them; Even ſo will God be of his people. <hi>As an Eagle ſtirrs up her neſt, flutters over her young, ſpreads abroad her wings, bears them on her wings,</hi> &amp;c. Deut. 32.11. And ſo Matth. 23.37. <hi>O Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, Jeruſalem, How often would I have gathered thee to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, as an hen gathereth her chickens under her wings!</hi> That is, with very much affection of and regard unto thee, He that toucheth you, toucheth the apple of mine eye <hi>Zechar.</hi> 2.8, 9. Or againe; as <hi>Birds flying,</hi> that is with a great deale <hi>of ſwiftneſſe,</hi> and ſpeed for the accompliſhment of it, In <hi>Pſal.</hi> 125.2. It is ſaid, that as <hi>The mountaines are round about</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>ſo is the Lord round about his people, from henceforth even for ever.</hi> The <hi>Mountaines</hi> round about <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> they are for the <hi>Defence</hi> and ſecurity of it, even ſo is the Lord himſelfe unto it, and a great deale more; <hi>For the Mountaines ſhall depart, and the hills ſhall be removed, but my kindneſſe ſhall not depart from thee,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ſaith the Lord, that hath mercy on thee,</hi> Iſa. 54.10.</p>
            <p>This ſerves to diſcover to us the happineſſe and priviledge of Gods people,<note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</note> and their advantage a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove other men. <hi>Happy art thou O Iſrael, who is like unto thee, O people ſaved by the Lord, who is the ſhield of thine help, and who is the ſword of thine excellency! Duet.</hi> 33.29. As for other people in the world, there's no great care taken of them, for the defence and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of them. Oh but <hi>the Church,</hi> that's ſure to be defended, what ever becomes of <hi>Babylon,</hi> God will be ſure to look after <hi>Zion,</hi> and what ever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes of <hi>Lachiſh,</hi> God will be ſure to defend <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> and to provide for the ſafety of it. Indeed, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:99989:6"/>places and perſons may <hi>occaſionally,</hi> and acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentally partake of the protection of the <hi>Church;</hi> wicked, and ungodly men, who are intermixt with the people of God, they doe partake of defence <hi>with</hi> them, and defence <hi>from</hi> them, as curſed <hi>Cham</hi> from his abode in the <hi>Arke,</hi> but it is not they, which are ſo much aimed at, or intended in this preſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; no, but Gods people themſelves, and the City, by which his Name is call'd on. He will defend <hi>this City</hi> eſpecially; and this he will not be failing to it, in the defending of it, whiles He ſayes He <hi>will</hi> doe it, He hereby ſignifies his <hi>Purpoſe</hi> about it. It is not onely a word of <hi>Intimation,</hi> but alſo of <hi>Reſolution,</hi> and that peremptory which cannot be fruſtrated, or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointed.</p>
            <p>If againſt this ſhall now be objected,<note place="margin">An Objection Anſwered.</note> that experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence oftentimes proves the contrary; ſo that not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding this promiſe here made, and this point maintained by us, there is not alwayes this defence vouchſafed, but that the people of God are, for all that, involved in ſundry, and frequent evills; To this we anſwer, that ſtill the promiſe of God ſtands ſure, <hi>I will defend this City:</hi> Becauſe as all other con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditionall promiſes beſides, it holds good for <hi>the moſt part,</hi> and ſo farr forth as may beſt conſiſt, both with the Honour and <hi>Glory of God,</hi> and the greateſt <hi>welfare</hi> of his people, This is a moſt certaine Truth; That God will be no way wanting to his Servants in the reaſonable defence of them. <hi>The Lord God is a Sun and ſhield;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 84.12.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord will give Grace and Glory, no Good thing will he withold from them that walke uprightly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is matter of very great comfort,<note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</note> and incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to them, which may make them to goe on with chearfulneſſe, and reſolution in his ſervice;
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:99989:6"/>Fear and apprehenſion of danger, it is a grand ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction to performances. Where men cannot think themſelves ſafe, they cannot there ſo quietly act, or undertake what belongs unto them; But, now this is the happineſſe of Gods people, that they ſhall be kept and preſerved from danger: whiles they walk in his <hi>wayes,</hi> they are ſure to have his <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection;</hi> Not only <hi>Cityes,</hi> and Publique places in Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, but particular <hi>Perſons;</hi> eſpecially as their work is larger, and of more Generall concernment. <hi>Publique</hi> Perſons they being themſelves of Publique intereſt, and the Good and welfare of the Publique being in ſome manner wrapt up in them, they doe therefore accordingly partake of the Benefit, and comfort of thoſe promiſes, which are made to Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Relations, whether in Church or Common wealth. <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> in the diſcharge of <hi>their</hi> places, and <hi>Miniſters</hi> in the diſcharge of <hi>theirs;</hi> The De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the City, it is the Defence alſo of <hi>them</hi> who are in a ſpeciall, and more then ordinary conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on comprehended in it. And thus ye ſhall find it to be ſet even by the Scripture it ſelfe in thoſe Incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragements, which are therein given unto them. Thus in Gods expreſſion to <hi>Joſhua, Joſh.</hi> 1.5. <hi>There ſhall not any man be able to stand before thee all the dayes of thy life; As I was with Moſes, ſo will I be with thee, I will not leave thee nor forſake thee.</hi> And thus in Gods expreſſion to <hi>Paul.</hi> Acts 18.9, 10. <hi>Be not affraid, but ſpeake, and hold not thy peace; For I am with thee, and no man ſhall ſet on thee to hurt thee; For I have much people in this City.</hi> I have much people in this City; what was this to <hi>Pauls</hi> protection? Yes very much; not only by taking it of thoſe, which were Gods people <hi>already,</hi> and ſo likely to take his part againſt
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:99989:7"/>thoſe, which would ſet themſelves againſt him: but eſpecially underſtanding it of thoſe, which were Gods people in <hi>decree,</hi> to be converted, and wrought upon by <hi>Paul</hi> in his Miniſtry, which could not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt with the taking away of the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> life before that work was done by him. This is the great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of thoſe, which are the ſervants of God; that their <hi>Imployment</hi> is their <hi>ſecurity;</hi> and the more <hi>buſineſſe</hi> they have to doe for him, the more <hi>defence</hi> they ſhall receive <hi>from</hi> him. And this for the <hi>Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, This City,</hi> in the full acception, and conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it.</p>
            <p>Now as for the <hi>Defendant,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant.</note> that is here expreſt to be <hi>God</hi> himſelfe. It hath been <hi>intimated,</hi> and imply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>hitherto</hi> in that which we have ſpoken all this while of the Defence, and Protection it ſelf. But we may here now take a more <hi>particular</hi> view and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of it. It is not ſaid only: <hi>This City ſhall be defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded;</hi> which had been enough, as to the ſafety of the <hi>place;</hi> but <hi>I</hi> will defend this City, as pointing out the Principall Author, and Actor in the defence of it, <hi>It is God,</hi> and he alone that is, to any purpoſe, the Defender of the City, <hi>I the Lord doe keep it. I will water it every moment, leaſt any hurt it, I will keep it night and day,</hi> as he ſpeaks concerning his <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ineyard,</hi> Iſa. 27.3. It is true indeed, God does commonly make uſe of <hi>others</hi> to this purpoſe both <hi>Angells</hi> and <hi>men,</hi> which are Creatures. <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> they are in their places,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and <hi>ex officio</hi> the <hi>Defenders of the City,</hi> and therefore called in Scripture the <hi>Shields of the Earth,</hi> Pſal. 47.9. Becauſe as a <hi>Shield</hi> does defend the Perſon that bears it, and by taking the blow it ſelf does ward it off from him that uſes it, even ſo alſo <hi>Governours</hi> in the execution of their places, are Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:99989:7"/>of great <hi>Security</hi> to the People that partake of them. So alſo <hi>Counſellours</hi> and men of advice they are in like manner men of <hi>Protection. Wiſdome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccles 7.12.</note> (ſayes <hi>Solomon</hi>) is a <hi>Defence and, money is a Defence; but the Excellency of knowledge is that wiſdome giveth life to them that have it;</hi> which <hi>money</hi> without <hi>wiſdome</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not doe, though <hi>wiſedome</hi> can ſometimes without <hi>that: The poore wiſe man by his wiſdome delivered the City.</hi> Eccleſ. 9.15. <hi>And in the multitude of Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours is ſafety.</hi> Prov. 11.14. and Prov. 24.6. <hi>Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> and inferiour officers, they have a ſhare alſo in this defence; But yet theſe and all others with them, they fetch their ſtrength and aſſiſtance <hi>from God, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the LORD build the houſe, they labour in vaine that build it, except the LORD keep the the City, the watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man watcheth but in vaine.</hi> It is <hi>God</hi> muſt help the <hi>Builders;</hi> and it is <hi>God</hi> muſt keep the <hi>Keepers,</hi> and it is <hi>God</hi> muſt watch the <hi>Watchers:</hi> If we deſire to <hi>have</hi> an Houſe, it is he that muſt raiſe it; and if we deſire to <hi>keep</hi> an Houſe, it is He that muſt <hi>watch</hi> it: It can neither goe up without him, nor yet <hi>stand</hi> without him, neither an <hi>Houſe,</hi> nor whole <hi>City</hi> it ſelfe. We finde as I ſaid in the <hi>Pſalme</hi> before alledged, that Magiſtrates are call'd <hi>the ſhields of the Earth,</hi> but yet in the ſame place theſe ſhields are ſaid to <hi>belong to God.</hi> They belong to God to make them,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and they belong to God to keep them and they belong to God to uſe them, and to <hi>manage</hi> them, and to defend with them. A <hi>ſhield</hi> in a <hi>weak hand,</hi> is to little purpoſe but is eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtruck out and remooved, yea, but therefore doe theſe hold upon <hi>God,</hi> without which they are all in vaine.</p>
            <p>And as all defence is in vain without God, ſo none is in vaine with him; whenſoever he undertakes it,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:99989:8"/>there is <hi>ſafety</hi> and ſecurity enough even from his undertaking. This is alſo hinted to us in the <hi>Scope,</hi> and drift of the Text, where this <hi>I</hi> is to be taken not onely <hi>ſimply</hi> but <hi>emphatically.</hi> The Lord here for the comfort of his people, who were now inſulted over by their enemyes, and apt to be daunted by them ſets <hi>Himſelfe</hi> in a way of <hi>oppoſition</hi> to all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary attempts, as a ſufficient <hi>bulwark</hi> againſt them. What's <hi>Sennacherib</hi> to <hi>me?</hi> And what's <hi>Rabſhakeh</hi> to <hi>me?</hi> Or what's all <hi>Aſſyria</hi> to <hi>me?</hi> as long as <hi>I</hi> have taken upon me this <hi>City</hi> for the defence and protec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it, what evill can now happen unto it? or what <hi>Enemy</hi> in the aſſaulting of it, can <hi>prevaile</hi> againſt it? <hi>If God be for it, who can be againſt it?</hi> Or if he be to what <hi>purpoſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is further obſervable from the <hi>Canſall, FOR</hi> in the beginning of the verſe which joynes this, and the foregoing together; It was ſaid there, that <hi>Aſhur</hi> ſhould not come into this <hi>City</hi> nor <hi>ſhoot an arrow there nor come before it,</hi> &amp;c. Now it might be demanded, what might be the <hi>ground</hi> of ſo much conſidence in the conſideration of ſo much <hi>danger?</hi> This is here anſwer'd in the Text. For <hi>I</hi> will defend this City, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> It is no matter what may be the <hi>Danger,</hi> ſo long as <hi>God</hi> is the <hi>Defender,</hi> and undertaker, for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance from it, which holds as in caſe of <hi>Enemyes,</hi> ſo alſo of all other evills beſides, whether ſickneſſes, or famins or deſolations, or what ever we can name; Forafmuch as the <hi>Lord</hi> hath all theſe in his own hand, and they are at <hi>his</hi> diſpoſing therefore may the people of God in an holy manner triumph over them, and aſſure themſelves ſo farr forth as is fitting of preſervation from them. This is that which the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> bottoms on, and teaches <hi>us</hi> to bottom on to.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:99989:8"/>
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 115.9. <hi>O Iſraell truſt in the Lord, he is their help and their ſhield: O houſe of</hi> Aaron <hi>truſt in the Lord, he is their help and their ſhield. Te that feare the Lord truſt in the Lord, he is their help, and their ſhield.</hi> It is thrice repeated, for the better carrying of our minds there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto. And thus much of the mercy ſignified, as conſiderable in the <hi>Specification,</hi> or ſimple Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it: <hi>For I will defend this City.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond is in the <hi>Amplification</hi> or Extent,<note place="margin">2. <hi>The Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plification.</hi>
               </note> in theſe words; <hi>To ſave it.</hi> This is added to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer by way of further in largement, and explanation of it. And there are two things conſiderable in it; Firſt, The <hi>Efficacy</hi> of this Defence what it is, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto it <hi>attaines,</hi> And Secondly, <hi>The end</hi> of this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, what it is whereunto it <hi>drives,</hi> and which is propounded in it, and it is <hi>ſalvation</hi> in either of them.</p>
            <p>Firſt, For the <hi>Efficacy</hi> or effect of it,<note place="margin">1. <hi>The Effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy.</hi>
               </note> the thing whereunto it reaches or attaines, and that is to <hi>ſave;</hi> This is more then can be ſaid of all defendings in the world, they doe not all end in <hi>ſaving,</hi> there's many a <hi>Perſon,</hi> and Place, and City, which is held up for a while, which yet at laſt is not preſerv'd; becauſe there is not ſo much <hi>Power,</hi> or ſtrength or ability, as will amount to the preſerving of it; yea, but where <hi>God</hi> undertakes, it is ſo, where ever he will <hi>defend</hi> he <hi>ſaves;</hi> where he defends in the <hi>undertaking,</hi> he ſaves alſo in the accompliſhment. According to that againe in the prophet, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 31.5. <hi>Defending alſo he will deliver, and paſſing over he will preſerve.</hi> So Iſa. 26.1 <hi>In that day ſhall this Song be ſung in the Land of Judah; We have a strong City, Salvation will God prepare for Walls and Bulwarkes;</hi> His arme brought <hi>Salvation.</hi> Iſa. 59.26. <hi>Stand still and ſee his ſalvation,</hi> Exod. 14.13.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:99989:9"/>This is the excellency of the Lord; That he <hi>is mighty to ſave.</hi> Iſa. 63.1. <hi>His hand is not ſhortned that it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſave,</hi> Iſa. 59.2. No, <hi>But he is able to ſave to the utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt thoſe that come to him,</hi> both in ſpiritualls and temporalls too.</p>
            <p>This accordingly teaches his people to expect it from him,<note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</note> not to <hi>limit the holy one of Iſraell,</hi> or to call in Queſtion his power, to this purpoſe, as the diſtruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and unbelieving <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> ſometime did, but to embrace it, and to depend upon it. As the <hi>Church,</hi> Iſa. 25.9. <hi>Loe this is our God, we have wayted for him, and he will ſave us: This is the LORD, we have way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for him; we will be glad and rejoyce in his ſalvation.</hi> There's none that ever yet truſted, and depended upon God, as they ſhould doe, who were fruſtrated in this particular. <hi>The Lord is nigh unto all them that call upon him, to all that call upon him in truth. He will fulfill the deſire of them that feare him, He will alſo heare their cry, and will ſave them.</hi> He will ſave them in the actuall <hi>accompliſhment</hi> of ſalvation to them.</p>
            <p>This is the difference now betwixt God and men in this reſpect; <hi>Men</hi> they can uſe the <hi>meanes,</hi> but they cannot promiſe the <hi>ſucceſſe:</hi> They can ſet upon the <hi>undertaking</hi> but they cannot aſſure the <hi>Perfomance; Phyſitians</hi> can give <hi>Phyſicke,</hi> but they cannot give <hi>Health,</hi> and <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> can give <hi>Aſſiſtance,</hi> but they cannot give <hi>Diliverance,</hi> yea, but the <hi>Lord</hi> he can doe all theſe; Health and Victory, and Protection, and Salvation it ſelfe; not onely in the <hi>Endeavour</hi> but in the <hi>Event,</hi> defend to ſave; as to the <hi>Efficacy,</hi> or <hi>Effect</hi> of it, that's the <hi>Firſt</hi> Explication.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Second</hi> is the <hi>End,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>The End</hi>
               </note> or intent. I will defend it to <hi>ſave</hi> it, as ſignifiing Gods gracious <hi>aime,</hi> and drift, in the defending of it. There are defendings ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:99989:9"/>which as they doe not alwayes <hi>end</hi> in Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſo neither doe they alwayes <hi>tend</hi> to ſalvation, but rather no ſomewhat elſe, which is either contrary or different from it. Thus <hi>Enemies</hi> they ſometimes <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend</hi> thoſe perſons whom they take captive in War, but it is not ſo much to <hi>ſave</hi> them, as rather to make <hi>advantage</hi> of them, and ſometimes advantage <hi>againſt</hi> them, to abuſe them, and to exerciſe ſo much the greater cruelty upon them, as the <hi>Philiſtims</hi> did with <hi>Sampſon</hi> whom they kept to make themſelves <hi>Sport,</hi> and to inſult ſo much the more over him. <hi>Judg.</hi> 16.28. Thus we ſee how that all defending, or keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, it hath not <hi>ſaving</hi> with it, And as not with <hi>men,</hi> So not with <hi>God</hi> neither. The Lord he does not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend ſome people alwayes to <hi>ſave</hi> them, but rather in <hi>Indignation</hi> towards them. He keepes them from one Judgment that he may reſerve them for another, and that for a <hi>worſe,</hi> keepes them from the <hi>Peſtilence,</hi> that he may deliver them to the <hi>Famine,</hi> delivers them from the <hi>Famine,</hi> that he may give them up to the <hi>Sword,</hi> he ſhifts and changes their puniſhments but does not <hi>remove</hi> them, or take them away. Accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that expreſſion, Iſa. 24.17, 18. <hi>Feare and the pit, and the ſnare are upon thee, O Inhabitant of the earth. And it ſhall come to paſſe, that he who fleeth from the noiſe of the feare, ſhall fall into the Pit, And he that cometh out of the midſt of the Pit, ſhall be taken in the ſnare.</hi> Here's now <hi>defending,</hi> and evading, but yet ſtill <hi>Salvation</hi> farr enough from it either in the thing it ſelfe, or in the intention of him that vouchſafes it; yea but here in the <hi>Text</hi> it is <hi>otherwiſe,</hi> when the Lord ſaies concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> that he will defend that to ſave it, he ſignifies that he will defend it with the <hi>greateſt benefit,</hi> and advantage to it, as he ſpeaks ſometimes to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:99989:10"/>Bleſſing I will bleſſe thee, and multiplying I will multiply thee;</hi> that is, I will make thoſe things which are Bleſſings <hi>an Increaſe,</hi> in the <hi>ſhew,</hi> and <hi>purport</hi> of them, to be ſo indeed, in the <hi>Event</hi> and <hi>Effect,</hi> that thou maiſt finde them to be ſo to thy <hi>ſelfe,</hi> in thy owne <hi>experience.</hi> This is that which God promiſes to his people in his defending of them. Indeed they ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times make <hi>other</hi> interpretations of it; as if he defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded them to <hi>deſtroy</hi> them, rather then to <hi>ſave</hi> them. As the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in their <hi>murmurring</hi> and repining temper.<note place="margin">Numb. 21.5.</note> 
               <hi>He brought us out of Aegypt, that he might de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy us in the Wilderneſſe.</hi> Yea, but it was not ſo for all that; God had other <hi>intentions</hi> towards them. <hi>I know the thoughts that I thinke towards you,</hi> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>thoughts of peace, and not of evill, to give you an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected end,</hi> Jer. 29.11. <hi>Men</hi> in their curteſies they are many times <hi>falſe and uncertain:</hi> If they doe one kindneſſe, they'l doe ſometimes <hi>two unkindneſſes for it,</hi> Perhaps, unkindneſſes <hi>in</hi> it. <hi>Timeo Danaos vel do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wa ferentes.</hi> but it is not ſo with <hi>God, He defends to ſave,</hi> and he ſaves in defending, eſpecially ſuch as are his <hi>people,</hi> and belong unto him.</p>
            <p>This is a very great happineſſe, and anſwerably ſhould be purſued by us;<note place="margin">Try all of our Conditions.</note> we ſhould examine not onely <hi>what</hi> we have, but upon <hi>what tearms</hi> we have it, to ſee that it be in mercy and love, and as a fruit of Gods good-will towards us, and as reliſhing his favor in it. <hi>This</hi> we may judge according as we are any thing <hi>made better</hi> by it, and doe any thing better <hi>with</hi> it Then are mercies <hi>ſaving,</hi> when they are <hi>ſanctifying,</hi> and <hi>ſanctified to us;</hi> Then they are beſtowed in <hi>favor,</hi> when they are improved in <hi>fruitfulneſſe,</hi> and made <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragements</hi> to further uſefulneſſe and cheerfulneſſe, and activity in Gods ſervice, otherwiſe we ſhall have
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:99989:10"/>but little comfort or ſatisfaction from them, but even <hi>our bleſſings will be curſt unto us.</hi> Malach. 2.2. which is the ſad condition of many wicked and ungodly Perſons, God defends them not ſo much to <hi>ſave</hi> them as rather to <hi>harden</hi> them, and ſo at laſt to <hi>ruine</hi> them, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 92.7. when the wicked ſpring as the graſſe, and all the workers of iniquity do flouriſh, it is that they ſhall be <hi>destroyed</hi> for ever. But as for the Servant, of God, he does not deale ſo with them, God hath not appointed them to <hi>wrath,</hi> but to <hi>Salvation,</hi> as the maine end of his diſpenſations towards them, which he promiſes here to this <hi>City</hi> of <hi>Judah;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Theſſ. 5.9.</note> 
               <hi>I will defend this City to SAVE it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For a further opening and inlargeing of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent paſſage to us,<note place="margin">The nature of the mercy.</note> we may here moreover take notice of the <hi>Nature</hi> and quality of the mercy it ſelf, and that is not of <hi>delivering</hi> mercy, but of <hi>preventing</hi> mercy. It is not ſaid I will <hi>reſcue</hi> this City but I will <hi>defend</hi> it, nor it is not ſaid, I will <hi>recover</hi> this City, but I will <hi>preſerve</hi> it. It is not ſaid, I'le let the <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> come <hi>in,</hi> and when he hath been <hi>in for a while,</hi> and done his pleaſure in it, i'le them expell him, and drive <hi>him out</hi> of it againe, no, but I will not ſuffer him ſo much as to <hi>enter</hi> into it, in the two verſes before the Text. <hi>He ſhall not come into this City nor ſhoot an arrow there, nor come before it with ſhields, nor cuſt a banke, against it, By the way that he came, by the ſame ſhall he returne, and ſhall not enter into the City</hi> (ſaith the Lord) See here, <hi>He ſhall not come into it, He ſhall not come into it;</hi> it's <hi>twice</hi> repeated to make it more remarkable; and that alſo with the <hi>Circumſtances</hi> of it, not <hi>ſhoot at it,</hi> not <hi>beſiege</hi> it, not encamp about it, ſuch is the tenderneſſe of God towards his people, as to keep off calamities from them.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:99989:11"/>
            <p>This is to be obſerved by them,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Preventing.</hi>
               </note> where it is, and to be acknowledged with greater Thankfulneſſe. <hi>Preventing</hi> mercies are the <hi>greateſt</hi> mercies of all: though ſuch is our <hi>weakneſſe,</hi> and corruption, that we are not alwayes ſo <hi>ſenſſible</hi> of them, nor doe ſo much lay them to heart: we are commonly more apprehenſive of <hi>Deliverances,</hi> then we are of <hi>Preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations;</hi> of health <hi>recover'd,</hi> then we are of health <hi>continued;</hi> and of ſafety or plenty <hi>reſtored,</hi> rather then of either of them <hi>maintain'd</hi> ſtill unto us. But that is rather I ſay from our <hi>Infirmity,</hi> then from the <hi>Nature</hi> of the things themſelves. If we take the thing ſimply in it ſelf, ſo <hi>continuance</hi> is more then <hi>reſtauration,</hi> becauſe it hath the ſweetneſſe of the <hi>Good</hi> in it, without experiences of the contrary <hi>Evill.</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed in ſome <hi>caſes,</hi> and accidentally, the <hi>latter</hi> may be much better then the <hi>former,</hi> and the reſtoring of a comfort, may be a greater mercy then the <hi>Conſtant injoyment:</hi> when as namely occaſionally from the temporary <hi>want</hi> of that Comfort a mans <hi>Heart</hi> is made ſo much the better; As when from ſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termiſſion of <hi>Health,</hi> a man has his <hi>Spirit</hi> hereby the more <hi>mortified,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.16.</note> and crucified, and eſtranged from the world, and he growes ſtronger in the <hi>inward</hi> man, which is hence <hi>renewed day by day:</hi> here the <hi>recovery</hi> may be more happy then the <hi>Continuance;</hi> But yet <hi>abſiractly</hi> and in the nature of the thing, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially alike <hi>ſanctified</hi> to us, ſo it is otherwiſe and to be apprehended by us: we ſhould have our hearts much drawn out in Thankfulneſſe for Gods <hi>with-holding</hi> of Evills from us, as it was here with this City before us. He did not <hi>reſcue</hi> them ſo much as <hi>defend</hi> them; It was not <hi>reſtoring</hi> mercy, but <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving;</hi> Not <hi>delivering</hi> mercy, but <hi>preventing.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:99989:11"/>
            <p>Againe further, Take <hi>one</hi> more,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Indefinite.</hi>
               </note> It was not <hi>deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined</hi> mercy, but <hi>indefinite, I will defend this City to ſave it;</hi> To ſave it? from what? It may be you will ſay from the fury, and rage of the <hi>King of Aſsyri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a;</hi> from the oppreſſions of a forraine Enemy. It is true indeed, that was the <hi>occaſion,</hi> and the maine and principall thing that was here intended, but yet that was not <hi>all.</hi> To <hi>defend and ſave,</hi> it is an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of large <hi>Extent,</hi> and comprehends <hi>many</hi> things in it. Thoſe who are kept from the Evills of <hi>warr,</hi> are kept from <hi>more</hi> then warr it ſelf, as having many <hi>other</hi> Evills with it, and conſequent to it. Now this was the <hi>State and condition</hi> of this people, and Gods carriage towards them. His mercy it was <hi>full,</hi> and compleat; He did not only <hi>defend</hi> them, but <hi>ſave</hi> them; Not <hi>restore</hi> them only, but <hi>preſerve</hi> them; Not preſerve them from <hi>one</hi> Evill, but from many <hi>more</hi> together with it; from the <hi>Sword</hi> of their Enemies, with all the miſchief attending upon it. Thus as in matter of <hi>Judgment</hi> where God <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins,</hi> he will make an <hi>End,</hi> ſo alſo in matter of <hi>mercy,</hi> where he <hi>undertakes,</hi> he will fully <hi>accompliſh,</hi> and bring to perfection.</p>
            <p>And ſo I have done with the <hi>first</hi> Generall part of the Text which is the mercy ſignified both in the <hi>Specification</hi> and the <hi>Extent. I will defend this City to ſave it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Second is the <hi>Ground,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The ſecond Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall.</note> or Motive for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring of it, and that is double; The one taken from <hi>God</hi> himſelf; <hi>For mine own ſake,</hi> and the other taken from his <hi>ſervant; For my ſervant Davids ſake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We begin with the Firſt, <hi>viz.</hi> The argument ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from <hi>God</hi> himſelf: <hi>For mine own ſake;</hi> where <hi>three</hi> things more by way of explication: Firſt,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:99989:12"/>For my <hi>mercies</hi> ſake,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Argument from God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</hi>
               </note> for the Honour of my <hi>free Grace.</hi> Secondly, for my <hi>Glories</hi> ſake, For the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of my <hi>Great Name.</hi> Thirdly, For my <hi>Truths</hi> ſake; For the honour of my <hi>Ancient promiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, For my <hi>mercies</hi> ſake; for the honour of my <hi>free Grace;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>For my mercy.</hi>
               </note> The beſt account of Gods actions is that which is reſolv'd into <hi>himſelf,</hi> but it holds good of <hi>none</hi> more then of his actions of <hi>Goodneſſe,</hi> and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour. Theſe take the chiefeſt riſe from <hi>himſelf,</hi> as the <hi>Ground</hi> of them.<note place="margin">1 Theſ. 5.10</note> 
               <hi>Even ſo O Father becauſe it ſeemed good in thy ſight,</hi> Mat. 11.26. It is true of <hi>ſpirituall,</hi> and eternall ſalvation, more eſpecially, of Gods de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending and ſaving from <hi>Hell,</hi> and from <hi>wrath to come,</hi> God does <hi>this</hi> for his <hi>own</hi> ſake indeed; but it is true alſo of ſalvation, which is <hi>Temporall,</hi> and ſo of this in the <hi>Text;</hi> when the Lord would ſhew a <hi>reaſon</hi> of his Favour, and kindneſſe to this people in preſerving them from the Violence of their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, He ſayes I will defend this City to ſave it <hi>for mine own ſake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When it is ſaid here; <hi>For mine own ſake;</hi> we are to take this expreſſion with <hi>reſtriction, ſignanter, &amp; excluſive;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Excluſive.</note> It ſhutts out this people themſelves as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>motives,</hi> or arguments hereunto. <hi>For mine own ſake,</hi> that is, not for theirs. Thus <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.22. <hi>I doe not this for your ſake, O Houſe of Iſrael, but for mine holy Names ſake.</hi> And againe <hi>v.</hi> 32. <hi>Not for your ſakes do I this</hi> (ſaith <hi>the Lord</hi> God) <hi>be it known unto you.</hi> And here two things more. Firſt, Nothing in you to <hi>deſerve</hi> ſo much from me. Secondly, Much in you to deſerve the contrary from me; nothing on your part of <hi>meritt,</hi> why it ſhould <hi>be:</hi> much on your part of <hi>provocation,</hi> why it ſhould <hi>not</hi> be.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Nothing in you of <hi>merit</hi> to deſerve it. It
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:99989:12"/>is the Conceit of moſt kind of men,<note place="margin">1. No merit in <hi>them.</hi>
               </note> when they have any thing more then ordinary from the hands of God, that it is from ſome ſpeciall <hi>worth</hi> in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; And ſo it is likely God ſaw that it was rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to be with this <hi>people;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 17.10.</note> for which cauſe he puts in this <hi>Caveat</hi> to prevent ſuch a miſtake in them. <hi>When we have done all we can, we muſt needs ſay we are unprofitable ſervants; we have done no more then was our Duty to doe,</hi> nor ſo much as that.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay.</hi> 64.6.</note> 
               <hi>All our righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe but as a menſtruous cloth, and as filthy ragges.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Theres much alſo of <hi>Provocation,</hi> and contrary behaviour; as no <hi>merit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merit</hi>
               </note> ſo a great deale of <hi>demerit.</hi> We are ſo far from deſerving <hi>from God,</hi> that we are obnoxious <hi>to</hi> him, and give him dayly occaſion (if he would take occaſion againſt us) utterly to conſume, and deſtroy us. Thus it was with this people of <hi>Jſrael:</hi> It is noted of them, that they <hi>provoked him to anger</hi> from day to day by their continuall abominations, and yet notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he followed them with his mercies; He ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them with a great deale of <hi>Patience,</hi> and bore <hi>with their manners in their milderneſſe</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as a <hi>Nurſe beareth or feedeth her children,</hi> Acts 13.41. Doing acts of courteſy for them, even whiles they were full of frowardneſſe, and rebellion againſt <hi>him,</hi> This is Gods way, and manner of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation.</p>
            <p>From whence we may therefore learne occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally how to deale with him,<note place="margin">Direction.</note> and to addreſſe our ſelves to him for any thing which we ſtand in need of. Alas, when we look upon <hi>our ſelves,</hi> and our own deſervings, there is nothing at all, which may incourage us,<note place="margin">1. How to deal-with <hi>God.</hi>
               </note> nay there is much rather which may <hi>diſhearten</hi> us, and keep us off; yea but heres now an
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:99989:13"/>
               <hi>argument</hi> which will take, and prevaile with him from <hi>his mercy, and free grace,</hi> and accordingly we ſhould uſe it to him. Lord, if thou wilt not doe it for <hi>our ſakes,</hi> yet do it at leaſt for thine <hi>own;</hi> Theres nothing in <hi>us</hi> to move thee, but theres a great deale in <hi>thy ſelf:</hi> Our <hi>deſerts</hi> are none, our <hi>provocations</hi> are many, but thy grace is above them all: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore according to the multitude of thy tender <hi>mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies</hi> be gracious to us; ſeeing God will do for it <hi>him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,</hi> let us not looſe ſuch an <hi>argument</hi> as this is for prevailing with him. Thus we ſhall find the <hi>church</hi> to doe, <hi>Jer.</hi> 14.7. <hi>O Lord though our iniquities testifie againſt us, doe thou it for thy Names ſake, for our bachſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings are many, wee have ſtnned againſt thee. And ſo David</hi> in his own particular; <hi>For thine Names ſake O Lord pardon mine iniquity for it is great:</hi> As knowing that this would work upon him, where nothing elſe would.</p>
            <p>And here as we have an <hi>argument</hi> to prevaile with <hi>God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. How with <hi>Satan.</hi>
               </note> ſo an anſwer to returne upon <hi>Satan,</hi> when he labours to diſcourage us from the ſuggeſtion of our own <hi>unworthineſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.13.</note> we may here tell him, that it is not upon ſuch <hi>termes</hi> that we deale with God, but upon the account of his own <hi>mercy, and grace;</hi> Let <hi>us</hi> be what we <hi>will</hi> be, yet he ſtill abides the <hi>ſame,</hi> and cannot deny himſelf.</p>
            <p>Againe, For his mercies ſake, that is, for his <hi>bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ells,</hi> and out of regard to his own <hi>compaſſions,</hi> which never faile. God will ſave his people, as being <hi>him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf</hi> intereſted in their ſufferings, and afflicted in all their afflictions; From whence he is ready to ſay with <hi>Eſther,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 63.9.</note> 
               <hi>How can I indure to ſee the destruction of my people,</hi> Eſther 8.6. And that's the firſt explication; <hi>For mine own ſake,</hi> i. e. <hi>for my mercies ſake, For the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:99989:13"/>of my <hi>Free Grace</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, For mine <hi>owne ſake,</hi> that is,<note place="margin">2 <hi>For my Glory.</hi>
               </note> for my <hi>Gloryes ſake,</hi> For the honour of my <hi>great Name.</hi> The preſervation of Gods people is for the glory of God himſelfe, which therefore carryes him to it: And that in two reſpects. Firſt, For his <hi>Glory,</hi> which would be otherwiſe neglected; He would have elſe none to ſerve him; Secondly, For his Glory which would be otherwiſe <hi>polluted;</hi> He would have elſe many to <hi>blaſpheme</hi> him.</p>
            <p>Firſt, God preſerves his people for his glory,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Leſt it be neglected.</hi>
               </note> which would be otherwiſe <hi>neglected;</hi> He would have elſe none to <hi>ſerve</hi> him. Take away the <hi>Church</hi> of God, and ye take away the <hi>Service</hi> of God, deſtroy his <hi>People,</hi> and ye conſequently deſtroy his <hi>Worſhip</hi> and his <hi>Name</hi> which is advanced by them, and by them <hi>alone.</hi> As for the reſt of the World, which are altogether ſtrangers to him, they care not what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes of him, nor of any honour which is done un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him: It is the <hi>Church</hi> which is <hi>called by his Name,</hi> by whom his <hi>Name is called upon.</hi> Now therefore as they are tender of <hi>him,</hi> even ſo is he alſo of <hi>them,</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſame conſideration, As <hi>Samuell</hi> tells the <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elites,</hi> 2 Sam. 12.22. <hi>The Lord will not for ſake his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, for his great Names ſake, becauſe it hath pleaſed the Lord to make you his people.</hi> And ſo Pſal. 132.13. <hi>The Lord hath choſen Zion, he hath deſired it for his habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; This is my reſt for ever, here will I dwell,</hi> &amp;c. It is ſpoken in reference to the <hi>Arke,</hi> and to the <hi>Temple,</hi> in the dedication of it, The <hi>Arke,</hi> of God it hath a <hi>Bleſſing</hi> of preſervation with it, which belongs unto it. 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.12. <hi>The Lord hath bleſſed the houſe of Obed-Edom and all that pertaine unto him, becauſe of the Arke of God,</hi> The ſame Priviledge alſo hath
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:99989:14"/>
               <hi>the Goſpell,</hi> and <hi>Evangellicall</hi> Adminiſtrations in the right uſe and improvement of them, to wit a <hi>preſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> Efficacy to the <hi>Contryes</hi> and <hi>Cityes,</hi> wherein they are, ſo farr forth as God is zealous for his <hi>Glory,</hi> and the continuance of his <hi>worſhip</hi> in the world ſo far forth will he defend his people, where his true wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and fear is maintain'd in the power and purity of it.</p>
            <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Leſt it be polluted.</hi>
               </note> For his <hi>Glory,</hi> as who would elſe have many to <hi>blaſpheme</hi> him, If God ſhould not defend his people, <hi>his enemies</hi> would be ready to <hi>reproach</hi> him, This is that which they have been ready ſtill to doe upon the leaſt advantage, we need to goe no further for an inſtance then the occaſion of the <hi>Text</hi> it ſelfe, in <hi>Senacherib</hi> and <hi>Rabſhakeh,</hi> Iſa. 36.15. <hi>Let not Hezekiah make you to truſt in the LORD, ſaying, The Lord will ſurely deliver us, This City ſhall not be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Where are they amongſt all the Gods that the Lord ſhould deliver Jeruſalem out of mine hand?</hi> here now were <hi>provokeing</hi> ſpeeches,<note place="margin">Improvement.</note> even to the diſhonour of God himſelf, and therefore it concern'd him to beſtir himſelfe, and to deliver his people for his Names ſake. Thus have the ſervants of God ſometimes made it an argument to him; As <hi>Moſes</hi> interceding for the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi>
               <note place="margin">3. <hi>By the Church.</hi>
               </note> Numb. 14, 15. <hi>Now if thou ſhalt kill all this people as one man, then the NATIONS which have heard the fame of thee will ſpeake ſaying, Becauſe the Lord was not able to bring this people into the Land, which he ſweare unto them, therefore hath he ſlain them,</hi> &amp;c. And ſo <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.12. <hi>Wherefore ſhould the Aegypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans ſay, for miſchiefe did he bring them out to ſlay them,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And</hi> ſo <hi>Joſhuah,</hi> in their diſcomfiture at <hi>At,</hi> Joſh. 7.9. <hi>The Canaanites and all the inhabitants of the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:99989:14"/>Land ſhall heare of it, and environ us round,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And what wilt thou doe unto thy GREAT NAME?</hi> ſtill the Name of God (as ready otherwiſe to be <hi>blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med</hi> by his enemies) is improved for the <hi>protection</hi> of his people.</p>
            <p>And as it has been improved by them to him,<note place="margin">2. <hi>By God himſelfe.</hi>
               </note> ſo it hath alſo been conſidered by himſelfe, even of his owne accord, as yee may ſee in <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.26, 27. Speaking there of the people of <hi>Iſrael, I ſaid I would ſeatter them into corners, I would make the remembrance of them to ceaſe from among men, were it not that I feared the wrath of the enemy, leſt the adverſaries ſhould behave themſelves ſtrangely, and least they ſhould ſay, our hand is high, and the Lord hath not done all this,</hi> Gods people are ſometimes <hi>accidentally</hi> ſo farr forth beholding to thier enemyes, as that their intollerable inſolences doe move God to keep them from theſe evils, which otherwiſe for their <hi>owne</hi> provocations would fall upon them. The <hi>Blaſphemyes</hi> of the <hi>Adverſary</hi> they are the <hi>ſhelter</hi> and defence of the <hi>Church;</hi> for mine <hi>owne ſake,</hi> (i. e.) <hi>for my gloryes ſake,</hi> for the honour of my <hi>Great Name;</hi> that on the one ſide it may be <hi>advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced,</hi> and that on the other ſide it may not be <hi>blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med,</hi> Thats the <hi>Second explication.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, For mine <hi>owne ſake;</hi> that is,<note place="margin">3. <hi>For my Truth.</hi>
               </note> for my <hi>Truths</hi> ſake, for the glory of mine <hi>Ancient promiſes</hi> The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> they were people of Gods <hi>Covenant,</hi> whom he had bound and ingaged himſelfe to, by many gracious and comfortable promiſes for the deliverance and preſervation of them; and now therefore in referrence to theſe, will he defend them to ſave them, God hath magnified his word, that is <hi>his promiſe</hi> above all his Name, Pſal. 138.2. Now this is that which <hi>He</hi> ſo much ſtands on, and makes
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:99989:15"/>it an argument to himſelfe. <hi>The NAME of the LORD is a ſtrong Tower, the righteous run unto it and are ſafe.</hi> Prov. 18.10. What's the <hi>Name</hi> of God? It is the <hi>True</hi> and faithfull one,<note place="margin">Temporall Promiſes.</note> The God that <hi>keeps Covenant.</hi> That's a great letter in his Name; and very much for the <hi>Comfort</hi> of his People,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Of protec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in Gener<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>He is faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full that hath promiſed,</hi> Heb. 10.23. <hi>His Truth ſhall be thy ſhield and buckler, Pſal.</hi> 91.4. How is the <hi>Truth</hi> of God a ſhield? Namely, as included in his <hi>Promiſe,</hi> which ingages him to the protection of his people, according as he hath declared himſelfe to them,<note place="margin">2. <hi>In Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular.</hi>
               </note> and that in all ſorts of conditions, <hi>John</hi> 5.19. <hi>He ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver thee in ſix troubles and in ſeven there ſhall no evill touch thee, In famine he ſhall redeeme thee from Death, and in Warr from the power of the Sword, Thou ſhalt be hid from the Scourge of the Tongue,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>From ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>At deſtruction and famine thou ſhalt laugh,</hi> So Pſal. 91.5. <hi>Thou ſhalt not be affraid of the terrour by night, nor of the arrow that flyeth by day, nor of the Peſtilence that waſteth in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, nor of the Deſtruction that walketh at noon-day, a thouſand ſhall fall at thy ſide, and ten thouſand at thy right hand but it ſhall not come nigh thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And againe,<note place="margin">2. <hi>From Fire.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>When thou paſſeſt through the waters, I will be with thee, and through the rivers they ſhall not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verflow thee, when thou walkeſt through the fire thou ſhalt not be burnt, neither ſhall the flame kindle upon thee.</hi> Iſa. 43.2. In theſe and many ſuch Scriptures have we the promiſes of <hi>Temporall</hi> protection made to the people of God, and the Lord does anſwerably hold himſelfe to be tyed and bound up by them, ſo farr forth as may beſt conſiſt with the Glory of his own holy Name, and the greateſt Good and <hi>Benefit</hi> of his people, and accordingly likewiſe may his people <hi>depend</hi> upon him for it, <hi>Lord remember thy Promiſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:99989:15"/>thy Servant upon which thou haſt cauſed me to hope. Pſ.</hi> 119.49. For mine <hi>own</hi> ſake, that is, for my <hi>Promiſe,</hi> That's the <hi>Third</hi> Explication. And ſo the <hi>Firſt</hi> Part of the Argument, for Gods defending, and ſaving of his people, to wit, which is taken from <hi>himſelfe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Second</hi> is taken from his <hi>Servant. And for my Servant Davids ſake, where before we goe any further,<note place="margin">Second Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid.</note> we may here by the way</hi> take notice of the <hi>Title,</hi> and hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ourable <hi>Appellation,</hi> which God puts upon <hi>David, My Servant David.</hi> It was not <hi>plain David,</hi> nor it was not <hi>King David,</hi> but <hi>David</hi> my <hi>Servant.</hi> God cannot let <hi>David</hi> paſſe without a Title of <hi>Honour;</hi> and God cannot put a greater <hi>Honour</hi> upon <hi>David,</hi> then by calling him his <hi>Servant, Gods Servant,</hi> it is the beſt <hi>Title,</hi> and it is the beſt <hi>Office,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In the <hi>Thing</hi> it ſelfe.</note> there's none like unto it, Not but that there are <hi>other</hi> Titles, and ſuch as are in their places alſo <hi>Honourable,</hi> and as <hi>Men</hi> to be acknowledged by us (<hi>Rligion</hi> does not deſtroy <hi>civility,</hi> but rather <hi>establiſhes</hi> it) but this is the <hi>Higheſt</hi> Title of all, eſpecially in a <hi>Spirituall</hi> ſenſe.</p>
            <p>There are two things obſervable in this expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; Firſt,<note place="margin">Gods Servant two wayes.</note> That <hi>David</hi> was Gods Servant for the thing it ſelfe; And Secondly, That God does here <hi>owne</hi> him, and acknowledge him to be ſo, as to the <hi>Title,</hi> and <hi>Apellation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, He was Gods Servant, <hi>His Servant David,</hi> There were two wayes in which <hi>David</hi> (as any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther beſides) might be ſaid to be the <hi>Servant of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>As to his work.</hi>
               </note> either in reference to his <hi>Particular</hi> calling, and the work wherein he was imployed, or in reference to his <hi>Generall</hi> calling, and the frame and temper of his <hi>heart</hi> in it.</p>
            <p>Firſt, As to his <hi>particular</hi> calling as a <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> and Governour of Gods people, He was the Servant
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:99989:16"/>of God <hi>thus, Magiſtrates,</hi> as they are Gods <hi>Vice-ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents</hi> ſo alſo his <hi>Servants,</hi> and his Servants <hi>therefore.</hi> This is a very great honour and Dignity to them, It is an Honour to be uſed by God though in works of an inferiour nature, not to be wholly uſeleſſe or laid aſide as <hi>broken veſſels</hi> wherein is no pleaſure, but the Higher the <hi>Service, ſtill the higher</hi> the <hi>Honour,</hi> and the Honour is <hi>from</hi> the Service, this is the Honour of thoſe which are in place of publique Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Authority, But an Honour and Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty with a duty belonging unto it, which is to approve themſelves to him whoſe Servants they are.</p>
            <p>But Secondly, As <hi>David</hi> was Gods Servant in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of his <hi>place,</hi> and imployment, So more eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in regard of his <hi>Spirit,</hi> and the frame of his heart, This was that which made him Gods Servant in a more <hi>Principall</hi> manner,<note place="margin">2. <hi>As to his Spirit.</hi>
               </note> and for which God does here ſo intitle him, There's a great deale of differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence betwixt <hi>my Servant David, and my Servant Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buchadneezzar,</hi> we ſhall finde in Scripture that <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buchadnezzar,</hi> was call'd Gods Servant, <hi>Jer.</hi> 25.9. <hi>Nebuchadnezzar the King of</hi> Babylon <hi>my Servant,</hi> Namely, as imployed by God in that work, which he uſed him for. There's not the <hi>worſt</hi> men that are but in a ſenſe, they may be <hi>Gods Servants,</hi> ſo farr forth as he does make uſe of them for the accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of thoſe Gracious ends, which he deſignes to himſelfe, God improves many mens parts and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and wiſedome, and intereſt, and eſtates beyond the thoughts of their owne minds; and ſo they are <hi>Servants</hi> to God in the matter, and ſubſtance of their Imployment. But this was not that which ſerved <hi>David,</hi> neither ſhould it ſerve any of us. He was the Servant of God in another manner then ſo; and that is in the Gracious <hi>frame</hi> of his ſoule, which was
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:99989:16"/>brought in ſubjection to God and whereby he aim'd at Gods glory in the ſervice of him, this was that which was <hi>Davids</hi> temper and which was <hi>Davids Honour,</hi> and in which ſenſe he might well ſay of himſelfe, as he ſometimes does; <hi>O Lord, truly I am thy Servant, I am thy Servant, &amp;c.</hi> Pſal. 116.16, <hi>David,</hi> He was Gods Servant in the <hi>Thing</hi> it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>And Secondly, God <hi>ownes him in it,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>In the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellation.</hi>
               </note> and ſo deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minates him for the <hi>Appellation; My Servant David.</hi> Thus God delights ſtill to ſpeake of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſefull,</hi> Perſons, <hi>Abraham</hi> my Servant, and <hi>Jacob</hi> my Servant, and <hi>Moſes</hi> my Servant, God ſpeakes of them as takeing a great deale of <hi>Pleaſure</hi> in their relation to him: He is not aſhamed to be call'd their God, nor that they ſhould be called his <hi>Servants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea, and that alſo even under ſome <hi>defects,</hi> and infirmities, and imperfections, As <hi>David</hi> here, he had ſometime his miſcarriages, yet truly repenting, and turning to God, and becoming a <hi>New-man,</hi> God owns him for his integrity, and uprightneſſe of heart, and reform'd converſation; <hi>My Servant</hi> ſtill, ſtill my <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant,</hi> My Servant <hi>David,</hi> ſo much for that.</p>
            <p>Now for the <hi>Argument</hi> it ſelfe, which is here uſed,<note place="margin">The Argument it ſelfe.</note> 
               <hi>For my ſervant Davids ſake,</hi> God joynes <hi>David</hi> with himſelfe as an argument for his goodneſſe to his people; why for <hi>Davids</hi> ſake? Namely, for his <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant</hi> with <hi>David,</hi> and ſo it referrs to that which we ſpake of before, concerning his <hi>Truth,</hi> Thus <hi>Pſal.</hi> 132.11. <hi>The Lord hath ſworn in truth to DAVID, he will not turne from it.</hi> We might here at large take notice of the Benefit, which <hi>Poſterity</hi> partake of from their Godly and Faithfull Predeceſſors; even then, when they are dead and deceaſed, <hi>DAVID</hi> was now gone, and in his grave many yeares ſince, yet this
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:99989:17"/>people they fare the better for his ſake; not for his preſent <hi>Interceſſions</hi> (as the <hi>Papiſts</hi> would faine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force it) but for his peculiar <hi>Intereſt</hi> and relation, and the <hi>COVENANT</hi> which was formerly made with him; <hi>Jeruſalem ſhall now be kept,</hi> and preſerved for <hi>Davids ſake,</hi> And ſo it is ſtill from time to time. <hi>The juſt man walks in his integrity, his children are bleſt after him, After him,</hi> Yea, and <hi>for</hi> him, and in refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence <hi>to</hi> him. God will ſhew mercy unto <hi>thouſands,</hi> of them that feare him, even unto the <hi>Third and Fourth Generation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this mention here of <hi>David</hi> in the Text hath ſomewhat a further reach in it,<note place="margin">The Spirituall ſince.</note> then as yet we have ſpoken unto; and that is as it points out <hi>Chriſt,</hi> of whom <hi>David</hi> was no more then a <hi>Type.</hi> And ſo it ſhewes us the true, and proper <hi>conveyance</hi> of all Good, and comfort to the <hi>Church.</hi> In theſe two ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions before us: <hi>For mine own ſake; and for my ſervant Davids ſake;</hi> we have two main <hi>Principles</hi> of faith exhibited to us; The one is the <hi>Spring,</hi> and Fountaine of our mercies: The other is, the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duit-pipe,</hi> and derivation. The <hi>Spring,</hi> and Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, thats the free <hi>grace,</hi> and goodneſſe of <hi>God;</hi> He does it for his <hi>own</hi> ſake. The Dirivation, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyance thats the mediation of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> He does if for his ſervant <hi>Davids</hi> ſake.</p>
            <p>The Summe of all is this; That all the Good, which <hi>Beleevers</hi> doe partake off from the hands of God,<note place="margin">The Summe.</note> it comes to them in the way of the <hi>New Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,</hi> which is founded in <hi>Chriſt; Who hath the Throne of David his Father given unto him,</hi> Luke 1, 32. And who <hi>ſits upon this Throne and Kingdome to order it, and to establiſh it for ever,</hi> Iſa. 9.6.7. <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who was figured by <hi>David</hi> and deſcended from him ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:99989:17"/>to the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> he hath changed <hi>Davids tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall</hi> Kingdome into an everlaſting, and <hi>ſpirituall</hi> one; And for <hi>his</hi> ſake will the Lord in this ſence defend <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to ſave it, that is, keep and preſerve his true <hi>Church</hi> from all the <hi>Adverſaryes,</hi> and Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of it. <hi>In his dayes ſhall Judah be ſaved, and Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem ſhall dwell ſafely, and this is the Name wherewith he ſhall be called The LORD O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R RIGHTEO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SNES,</hi> Jer. 23.6. and 33.16.</p>
            <p>Here's the great ſafety, and ſecurity of the <hi>Church</hi> of God,<note place="margin">The Safety of the Church.</note> that it ſtands upon a <hi>Covenant</hi> made with the <hi>Son of God.</hi> God cannot break with <hi>Christ,</hi> in whom all his promiſes are made <hi>yea, and amen,</hi> and therefore he cannot forbeare to protect, and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the <hi>Church.</hi> Therefore <hi>the Gates of Hell ſhall not be able to prevaile against it. Sennacherib, and Rabſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keh,</hi> and all the hoſt of the <hi>Aſſyrians,</hi> they ſhall not be able to fight againſt <hi>this City,</hi> ſo, as to overcome it; that is, <hi>Satan,</hi> and all his <hi>inſtruments,</hi> they ſhall never be able to <hi>overthrow</hi> it. God will put his <hi>Hook into their noſes, and his Bridle into their lipps, and turn them back by the way, in which they came.</hi> He hath <hi>ſent Redemption to his people:</hi> He hath <hi>comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded his CO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ENANT for ever. Holy, and Reverend is his Name,</hi> Pſal. 111.9.</p>
            <p>This is matter of <hi>Conſolation</hi> not only to the Church in <hi>Generall,</hi> and at large,<note place="margin">The Comfort of the Church.</note> but likewiſe to every true <hi>believer,</hi> who is a part, and member of it; For upon the ſame termes as God defends this <hi>City</hi> it ſelf, he does likewiſe defend every <hi>Citizen</hi> of it. Every good <hi>Chriſtian</hi> may aſſure himſelf of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation from all his <hi>Enemies</hi> from this <hi>Covenant,</hi> which God hath made with <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but I cannot now inſiſt upon <hi>this.</hi> That's the <hi>Second</hi> motive or
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:99989:18"/>argument for Gods defending this City to ſave it. Namely, which is taken from <hi>his ſervant,</hi> For <hi>my ſervant Davids ſake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall have quickly done with the <hi>Text,</hi> when I have taken notice of <hi>one</hi> thing more, and then pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to <hi>Application.</hi> And that is the <hi>manner,</hi> or way in which the Lord did accompliſh this promiſe,<note place="margin">The manner of the Churches preſervation.</note> which he here makes for the defence of this <hi>City.</hi> This will appeare to us out of the <hi>Context</hi> in the following verſe. <hi>Then the Angell of the Lord went forth, and ſmote in the Camp of the Aſſyrians an hundred fourſcore, and five thouſand.</hi> The <hi>Salvation</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> it is procured by the <hi>Ruine</hi> of the <hi>Enemy.</hi> The deſtruction of the <hi>Aſſyrians</hi> it is the Preſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>People</hi> of God. Theſe two are like a paire of <hi>Bucketts,</hi> or Ballances; when the one goes <hi>up,</hi> the other goes downe.</p>
            <p>The Reaſon of it is this;<note place="margin">The Reaſon.</note> Becauſe they are of <hi>Contrary</hi> intereſts, and conſiſt of contrary <hi>Principles,</hi> which cannot <hi>Cohaere,</hi> or hold together. They are like fire and water, which doe mutually take away each other. The <hi>ſeed of the Woman,</hi> and the <hi>ſeed of the Serpent</hi> are <hi>oppoſites.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is a point of very great <hi>Terror</hi> to the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es Enemies,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Terrour to the Enemies.</hi>
               </note> and ſhewes their ruine to be <hi>un-avoyd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able.</hi> If the people of God cannot be ſaved unleſſe their Adverſaries be <hi>deſtroy'd,</hi> then their Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries deſtruction is <hi>neceſſary,</hi> becauſe their own ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is <hi>infallible.</hi> Look upon what termes, the <hi>Church</hi> ſtands for <hi>ſafety,</hi> upon the ſame doe the <hi>Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies</hi> for <hi>undoeing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If it be ask't, why it pleaſes the Lord to take ſuch a Courſe as this is. We anſwer,</p>
            <p>Firſt for his <hi>own</hi> ſake, and the greater manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:99989:18"/>of <hi>his Power,</hi> and dominion in the world; God could (if he had ſo pleaſed) have defeated <hi>Aſhur,</hi> and yet not have deſtroyed them, hindred them from <hi>hurting Jeruſalem,</hi> and yet not have hurt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; yea but then this had not been ſo much for the advancement of his <hi>Power;</hi> which God delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to manifeſt towards them, as he did with <hi>Pharo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah.</hi> He would ſhew <hi>his Power in him,</hi> Rom 9.17. <hi>Be ſtill and know that I am God;</hi> I <hi>will be exalted among the Heathen:</hi> I will be exalted <hi>in the Earth,</hi> Pſal. 46.10.</p>
            <p>Secondly, for the comfort of <hi>his people.</hi> in their <hi>ſecurity,</hi> and greater ſatisfaction.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Comfort to Gods People.</hi>
               </note> If God had driven the <hi>Aſſyrians</hi> back, and kept them ſtill <hi>alive, Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> might ſtill have been <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>om what <hi>anxious,</hi> and ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitous about it, as thinking that they might haply <hi>recruit,</hi> and recover themſelves againe; now whiles they ſee them <hi>dead</hi> and deſtroy'd before their eyes, here this ſollicitude is taken off from them, and they are now ſenſibly aſſured of this promiſe, which God made unto them; that he would <hi>defend them to ſave them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now in that it is here further ſaid:<note place="margin">The Inſtrument</note> That this was done by the <hi>Angell of the</hi> Lord; it teaches us how theſe <hi>Glorious Spirits</hi> are miniſtring to the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the <hi>Church,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 78.49.</note> and active in the preſervation of it. Look, as ſometimes they are inſtruments of Gods <hi>Corrections.</hi> He <hi>ſent evill Angells amongſt them.</hi> not evill in regard of their <hi>Nature,</hi> and in reference to <hi>ſinne,</hi> but evill in regard of their <hi>Effects,</hi> and in reference to <hi>puniſhment,</hi> ſo are they alſo inſtruments of Gods <hi>preſervation;</hi> both in the <hi>ſheathing</hi> the ſword, and in <hi>drawing</hi> it: In <hi>ſheathing</hi> it as to the <hi>ſparing</hi> of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> in <hi>Davids</hi> time. In <hi>drawing</hi> it as
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:99989:19"/>to the <hi>defending</hi> of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> now in the Time of <hi>Hezekiah.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam, 24.16.</note> So much may be ſpoken of <hi>that.</hi> And ſo much alſo of the <hi>Text</hi> it ſelf.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>And now for the Application of the <hi>Text</hi> to the preſent <hi>Occaſion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THat which hath been hitherto ſaid,<note place="margin">The Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the Text to the Occaſion.</note> in <hi>that</hi> by way of <hi>promiſe,</hi> the ſame is made good in <hi>this</hi> by way of <hi>accompliſhment.</hi> And that which was true of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> it is abundantly true of <hi>London</hi> in all particulars. <hi>The Lord hath defended this City to ſave it, for his owne ſake,</hi> &amp;c. Defending and ſaving (as I told you) is a large word &amp; of indefinite ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cation, and truly we have found it ſo for <hi>our ſelves</hi> in the full latitude of it. There's no evill which any City could be well defended and ſaved from, but we have had our ſhare and intereſt in that Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>Wee'l begin with that which is next at hand,<note place="margin">Preſervation.</note> and in the ſcope of the <hi>Text,</hi> the evills and callamities of <hi>Warr,</hi> How hath the Lord ſaved us, and defended us from theſe!<note place="margin">From <hi>War.</hi>
                  </note> Indeed we have <hi>heard</hi> of ſuch a thing as this is, we have had the <hi>Rumors of Warr,</hi> amongſt us but we never yet felt the <hi>ſmart</hi> of it, as <hi>other</hi> parts of the Nation have done; we have had the <hi>Alarme,</hi> but we never yet came to the <hi>Enconnter,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.6.</note> no compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of our walls, no battering of our Forts, no plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering of our houſes, no demoliſhing of our Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les no ſlaying of our Wives and Children before our eyes, nor carrying of our ſelves as Captives into a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Countrey; when almoſt all the Land beſides as it were upon a light flame,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.27.</note> 
                  <hi>Not an haire of our head ſinged, nor our our coats changed, nor the ſmell of fire paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing upon us.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:99989:19"/>
               <p>And as through the goodneſſe of God we have been prevented from <hi>forraine invaſions,</hi> ſo likewiſe, from <hi>domeſtick combuſtions,</hi> and tumults amongſt our ſelves. <hi>No breaking in,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 144.4</note> 
                  <hi>nor going our nor complaining in our ſtreets.</hi> It is a thing wonderfull to conſider, how in ſuch a <hi>Populous</hi> City as this is, wherein there are ſuch multitudes of <hi>Perſons,</hi> and withall ſuch va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rietys of <hi>Intereſts,</hi> and difference, and contrariety of affections, yet not withſtanding there ſhould be ſo much outward agreement, and correſpondency and externall complyance, as is eaſie to be obſerv'd; Where againe almoſt in all the world can a man walk with ſo much ſafety at all times and houres of the <hi>night,</hi> without feare, or moleſtation, as he may doe in the City of <hi>London,</hi> or where may he ſtay in his <hi>Houſe</hi> with ſo much ſecurity!</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>War,</hi> It does not uſually goe <hi>alone,</hi> but for the moſt part hath other evills, and calamityes atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding upon it. The Scripture points out two eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially, The Famine and the Peſtilence; as in that eminent place of the Prophet, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 7.15. <hi>The ſword is without, and the Pestilence and the Famine within. He that is in the Field ſhall dye with the ſword, and he that's in the City, Famine and Peſtilence ſhall devoure him.</hi> This hath been the caſe of <hi>others,</hi> But this caſe hath not been <hi>ours,</hi> we have not known what Famine meant nor Peſtilence neither.</p>
               <p>For <hi>Famine,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">From <hi>Famine.</hi>
                  </note> though it is true it hath been an uſual conſequent of <hi>Warr,</hi> and of <hi>Civill</hi> warr, more eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, yet it hath been ſo with us here in this <hi>Land,</hi> nor ſo conſequently here in this <hi>City,</hi> nay we have been ſo far from being troubled with <hi>Famine,</hi> as that <hi>ſome</hi> of us (the more ſhame for us) we have rather been troubled at <hi>Plenty,</hi> and almoſt hungred for
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:99989:20"/>
                  <hi>Famine</hi> it ſelfe, ſo great hath been the abundance of Food and Proviſion amongſt us, which God hath beſtowed upon us. Yea, and that in ſuch <hi>Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances</hi> to, as wherein the <hi>Contrary</hi> might rather have been expected, we have had years of <hi>Drought,</hi> and yet not years of <hi>Dearth;</hi> wanted <hi>Water,</hi> and yet not wanted <hi>Bread.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And for the <hi>Peſtilence,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">From <hi>Peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence.</hi>
                  </note> which is the buiſineſſe that we doe more particularly take notice of this day, in this our ſolemn meeting, we have cauſe to take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of it indeed, as little leſſe then a miracle it ſelf, our preſervation from it; eſpecially ſo long together as we have been without it in theſe latter years, whiles other Countryes and Nations about us have been ſo ſorely viſited with it.</p>
               <p>Eſpecially if we ſhall alſo further add the forerun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and prognoſtications which we have had of it in inferiour diſeaſes, as ſmall-pox meaſles and the like, yet not leaving this other in their roome as they are uſually obſerv'd to doe, but ſo kindly part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with us, like the thaw of ſome great froſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a raine following upon it.</p>
               <p>That we ſhould have ſo much <hi>Health</hi> in ſo much <hi>Company;</hi> the number of <hi>Houſes and Inhabitants</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed unmeaſurably; The number of the <hi>Dead</hi> not increaſed, but rather diminiſhed; Take but this laſt week for an inſtance, wherein the ſumme of all the Buryalls within the City and Suburbs and Libertyes, and out-Pariſhes of it doth not come up to the number of two hundred in the whole ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count.</p>
               <p>Add to this (which is added in the occaſion) our late remarkable preſervations from <hi>Fire,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">From <hi>Fire.</hi>
                  </note> which for ſome time we had been afflicted withall,<note place="margin">Tower-ſtreet.</note> we
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:99989:20"/>know how many ſad and fearfull accidents of this kinde did for a while happen unto us in ſundry em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inent and ſeattered places of the <hi>City,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Thread needle-ſtreet, Fleet-ſtreet. Bermondſey-ſtreet. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> which in a ſort was become another <hi>Taberah,</hi> to us, Numb. 11.2. God hath gratiouſly quench't and extenguiſh theſe flames amongſt us, and he hath done it alſo as a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne of Prayer; as he did there with his people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> in <hi>v.</hi> 2. of that Chapter, It is not a meere <hi>co-in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidence,</hi> but a <hi>relative</hi> providence, &amp; ſo we are to take it; <hi>Faith,</hi> whereof Prayer is the <hi>flame,</hi> it hath quen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched the violence of <hi>fire,</hi> Heb. 11.34. And we are to bleſſe God for his acceptance of it. That we have neither the fire in our <hi>Bon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s,</hi> in burning and inflaming <hi>distempers,</hi> nor yet the fire in our <hi>Houſes</hi> in thoſe terrible and lamentable <hi>Conflagrations,</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>Dever,</hi> nor the <hi>reſheph; The Peſtilence which goes before him, nor the burning coales which goe forth at his feet,</hi> as <hi>Officers,</hi> and Attendants upon him, both before and behinde, <hi>Habback.</hi> 3.5. But that each of theſe have been kept off from us, and reſtrain'd from their violence amongſt us, what does this but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare Gods ſpeciall care and tenderneſſe over us, for the defence and preſervation of us? And how much does it concerne you all to conſider it and to lay it to heart, and to be affected with it! ye goe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Countrey,</hi> and ye find your houſes and families ſafe <hi>there;</hi> ye come back againe to the City, and ye finde your houſes and familyes ſafe <hi>here;</hi> ye change your <hi>Places,</hi> but ye doe not change your <hi>Protection,</hi> nor your condition with them. And this ye doe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in a <hi>Variety,</hi> and ſucceſſion of <hi>Time,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 65.12.</note> Summer after Winter, and Winter after Summer, and one year after another; God <hi>Crownes</hi> your yeares with his <hi>Goodneſſe,</hi> and his pathes dropp fatneſſe to you,</p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:99989:21"/>
               <p>I ſay it is God that does it and he <hi>excluſively;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">By God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone-</note> it is as true of us, as ever it was of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> He that is <hi>our God,</hi> is <hi>the God of our ſalvation, and to God the Lord belong the iſſues from Death,</hi> Pſ. 68.20. But what is that which hath <hi>mooved</hi> him, &amp; perſwaded him and incouraged him hereunto all this while, Perhaps it hath been ſomewhat in us, who have deſerved as much at his hands. It may be it hath been our ſtrictneſſe and exactneſſe of converſation before him; Our care of his worſhip, our Vindication of his Truth, our obſervation of his Sabbaths, our Honor of his Ordinances, our reſpect to his Servants our love of his Children, Perchance it hath been our charity, our humility, our ſobriety, our integrity, our zeale, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Which hath ſo far taken with him, and prevailed upon him, Surely, it is becauſe he hath not ſpyed in us thoſe errors, nor luſts, nor filthineſſe; nor horrible abominations; which He hath ſeen, and beheld in ſome other places and times;<note place="margin">Eſay. 1.9.</note> Oh Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved! ſhould the Lord but have gone by this <hi>Rule,</hi> I fear this City had been in its aſhes long before now, <hi>We had been as Sodom and had been made like unto Gomorrah.</hi> Not but that God has a <hi>Number,</hi> not a ſmal but a very great remnant of thoſe that truly feare him amongſt us,<note place="margin">Act. 18.29.</note> 
                  <hi>He hath much people in this City.</hi> But if we ſpeak of the common frame of mens ſpirits, and tenour of their lives,<note place="margin">For his own ſake.</note> we ſhall find it to be for other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, in ſomuch that the ſafety which we injoy, muſt be reſolved into the Free-grace and goodneſſe of God towards us; He hath defended us and ſaved us for his <hi>own ſake,</hi> as the proper <hi>Ground</hi> and <hi>Motive</hi> to it.</p>
               <p>And yet I muſt alſo add,<note place="margin">For his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant <hi>Davids</hi> ſake.</note> as himſelfe does here in the Text, <hi>For his ſervant Davids ſake;</hi> too we injoy the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:99989:21"/>Benefit of the graces of the Godly <hi>Martyrs,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther holy Perſons, <hi>our Fore Fathers</hi> in former ages who by their Prayers and votes for us, whiles they were here alive did reſerve a ſpeciall Bleſſing for us in theſe ſucceeding times; As we are not the worſe neither for the faithfull Servants of God, which at this day reſide amongſt us, and are mingled with us, who both keep of many judgements from us, which we otherwiſe <hi>deſerve,</hi> and ſecure many mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies to us, which we might otherwiſe loſe.</p>
               <p>Now what is the reſult of all this to our ſelves? Namely, that which is the proper work and buiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of our coming together, even to labour to get our hearts inlarged in thankfulneſſe to God for it, It is a work well becoming the <hi>Repreſentative body</hi> of the City, as ye are now met together this day, and wherein ye have very happily conſulted the welfare of it, &amp; of your ſelves, God expects ſuch acts as theſe from us, anſwerable to his goodneſſe to us, eſpecially upon our intreatyes of him; Forasmuch as we had humbled our ſelves before God, for the vouchſafing of theſe mercyes to us (as ſometimes we had done) we cannot in all reaſon but returne our acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgements to him for the beſtowing of them Every day of humiliation, whenſoever it obtains its effect hath a day of thanksgiving in courſe and of right belonging unto it. They that ſeek the Lord muſt praiſe him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22.26.</p>
               <p>Among many other matters beſides as I have already mentioned which you have not excluded, there are two which ye have eſpecially intended, The preſervation of the City from <hi>Fier,</hi> and the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of it from ſickneſſe, and principally thoſe contagious diſeaſes, which have raged in other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:99989:22"/>of the world; and it is a very good courſe which is here taken by you, in the ſerious improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of it for the preventing of ſuch judgements from your ſelves by thankfulneſſe and humble <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>precation,</hi> as the Captaine of fifty, to <hi>Elijah,</hi> in 2 <hi>King.</hi> 1.13. This is that which we are to doe at this time; and that not for a day only, but all our lives. There's no ſuch thankfulneſſe as reformation, and and amendment of life.<note place="margin">1 Sam 15.22</note> 
                  <hi>To obey is better then to ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice; and to bearken then the fat of Rams.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 King, 8.28.</note> Alas Beloved, what will it availe us,<note place="margin">Eſay. 9.18.</note> to be freed from the plague of the <hi>Body,</hi> and to be infected with the plague of the <hi>Heart?</hi> or to be freed from the firing of our Houſes, and to be inflamed with the fire of <hi>lust?</hi> of wrath, of contention, of revenge, of wickedneſſe, <hi>which burnes as a fier? Scornfull Perſons</hi> (as all <hi>ungodly</hi> men are both <hi>actively,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 29.8.</note> and <hi>paſſively</hi>) they <hi>ſet a City on fire,</hi> as <hi>Solomon</hi> tells us, <hi>But wiſe men,</hi> that is, thoſe which are Gratious and Faithfull, <hi>they turne away wrath.</hi> This let <hi>us</hi> be carefull to doe. That ſo as God hath delivered <hi>us formerly,</hi> ſo he may pleaſe to deliver <hi>us ſtill;</hi> and may ſay to <hi>us</hi> in the words of the Text in the future expreſſion; <hi>I will defend this City to ſave it,</hi> That is; I will <hi>continually</hi> defend it, from fire, and ſword, and peſtilence and ſuch evills <hi>as</hi> thoſe are.</p>
               <p>Yea, let <hi>us</hi> anſwer this goodneſſe of God to <hi>us</hi> in a <hi>ſutable</hi> and proportionable <hi>Improvement,</hi> Here are now two great mercies together, which we now celebrate, The one, that our <hi>Houſes</hi> are not <hi>burnt downe.</hi> And the other, that our <hi>Houſes</hi> are not <hi>ſhut up,</hi> Now each of theſe calls for anſwerable car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage and converſation, on our behalfe, How ſhould this now ingage <hi>us</hi> to make our <hi>Houſes</hi> and <hi>Familyes</hi>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:99989:22"/>to be the receptacles and habitations of <hi>Holineſſe,</hi> and to devote them to his worſhip and ſervice; that as they ſtand, ſo they may ſtand for <hi>Him,</hi> and his Spirit to dwell and reſide in.</p>
               <p>And ſo for our preſervation from <hi>Pestilence,</hi> and ſuch like diſtempers, what an ingagement is this to us to fruitfulneſſe of <hi>ſociety</hi> and <hi>communion</hi> one with another! To the frequenting of the <hi>publique Aſſemblyes:</hi> and congregations of the people of God, We need not now to be affraid of the breath one of another or of coming into one anothers <hi>company,</hi> which people in ſuch times and caſes and conditions are wont to be.</p>
               <p>But yet withall, whiles we are <hi>thankfull for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverances,</hi> it concerns us to tremble at <hi>judgements</hi> The experiences of <hi>Italy</hi> and of <hi>Rome,</hi> eſpecially which is myſticall <hi>Babylon</hi> the mother of Harlots, and Abominations of the earth; partake not in her ſinnes, that ſo we may not partake in her plagues. The ſinnes of <hi>Italy</hi> in <hi>England,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Revel. 17.5. Revel. 18.4.</note> are worſe then in their <hi>proper place;</hi> by how much our profeſſion is better, and our Religion purer, and our Ingage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments more.</p>
               <p>Therefore let us renew our <hi>Covenants</hi> with God this day, and labour to be every way anſwerable to his providences towards us; ſeeing <hi>He</hi> hath defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>us,</hi> let <hi>us</hi> alſo defend <hi>him</hi> in his Truth, and worſhip and Servants. And ſeeing it is <hi>God alone</hi> that can defend us, that is, defend us to ſave us, let us hide our ſelves all we can under <hi>his</hi> ſhelter, and wings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> We are now in the turn &amp; revolution of <hi>another year,</hi> which we know not what it may bring forth; Oh but if we can get but a ſhare and porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in <hi>God,</hi> we ſhall be provided againſt all occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:99989:23"/>whatſoever they may be. <hi>He that dwelleth in the ſecret place of the moſt high ſhall abide under the ſhadow of the Almighty; He ſhall ſay unto the Lord, he is my Refuge, my God in him will I truſt.</hi> Pſal. 91.1, 2.</p>
               <p>There are two things which lyes upon us in this particular, to be purſued by us. The one is <hi>Intereſt</hi> in God. And the other is <hi>Communion</hi> with him. The former as a foundation to the latter. And the latter as a <hi>Perfection</hi> of the former.</p>
               <p>Firſt, Accquaintance and <hi>Intereſt</hi> in God through <hi>Jeſus Chriſt, Accquaint now thy ſelfe with him, and be at peace, Job</hi> 22.21. There is nothing more miſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in times of publique danger or calamity, then for a man to be a <hi>ſtranger</hi> to God, and un-acquainted with him; It is ſad and ill at any time, but it is then ſo more eſpecially; that ſo we may by all meanes take heed of being guilty of it. Remember, that it is for <hi>Davids ſake,</hi> take this <hi>City</hi> is defended and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; therefore thoſe who have no portion in this <hi>David,</hi> they can expect none of this <hi>defence. Christ</hi> will owne none but his <hi>Members,</hi> in the day of his <hi>wrath,</hi> and <hi>them</hi> He will be ſure to owne, one way or other. <hi>Then happy are all they that put their Truſt in him.</hi> Lord I am thine, ſave me, that's the beſt plea of all. Pſal. 119.94.</p>
               <p>Secondly, as <hi>Intereſt</hi> in God, ſo likewiſe actuall <hi>Communion</hi> with him, let us preſerve that alſo. As there ſhould not be in us a ſtrangneſſe of <hi>condition</hi> ſo neither a ſtrangneſſe of <hi>Spirit,</hi> or <hi>converſation</hi> in ſuch times as theſe are, but we ſhould ſtill be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to keep up our hearts in a bleſſed and conſtant frame of recourſe unto him; that ſo, what ever may befall us, it may be ſure to goe well with us; which is the difference betwixt the <hi>children of God,</hi> and
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:99989:23"/>other men; As for <hi>other</hi> People; Carnall, and worldly perſons, they are well in times of <hi>Freedome,</hi> and ſecurity, when theres no plague, or judgement ſtirring abroad, <hi>then</hi> they can make a ſhift to doe as wel as any men elſe, and as they think <hi>better</hi> too; yea but how is it with them in times of <hi>Trouble,</hi> and ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe indeed? <hi>Here</hi> they are all <hi>amort,</hi> and know not which way to turn themſelves: as thoſe which ſwagger moſt in a <hi>Calme,</hi> in a <hi>Storme</hi> are at their wits end; ſo is it with <hi>ſuch</hi> kind of men. <hi>Eut I know it ſhall be well with them that fear the Lord, that fear before him,</hi> as the <hi>Preacher</hi> tells us, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 8.12. This is the Excellency of a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> eſpecially liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the <hi>Power</hi> of Chriſtianity, that he can in ſome manner hold up even in <hi>bad</hi> times, and in <hi>bad condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</hi> He can be ſafe in the midſt of evills, and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities themſelves: ſafe, not only <hi>from</hi> them, but <hi>in</hi> them, yea and <hi>under</hi> them too, as it may be with him. The ſervants of God have this privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that thoſe things, which are evill in <hi>themſelvs,</hi> yet they are not evill to <hi>them,</hi> as having all Eſtates ſanctified to them through Chriſt. That which is a <hi>Plague</hi> in the nature of the <hi>Diſeaſe,</hi> and the <hi>Phyſicall</hi> conſideration of it, yet it is not a plague to <hi>them,</hi> in regard to Gods ordering it to them, as having the <hi>Spirituall venome</hi> and malignity taken out of it for them; and ſo for any thing elſe beſides; A Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an ha's learnt to commend all he <hi>ha's</hi> or <hi>is</hi> to the wiſe and holy providence of a gracious God; His <hi>Times</hi> are in Gods hands, and ſo he is not in thral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to ſickneſſe: and his Eſtates in Gods hands, and ſo he is not under the power of <hi>Fire,</hi> or wind, or water, or malice, or any other caſualty whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever; Theres nothing can abſolutely hurt him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:99989:24"/>he is <hi>Good,</hi> and right <hi>himſelfe.</hi> But I cannot preſſe theſe things at this time.</p>
               <p>To return to that which we ſpake of before,<note place="margin">The Concluſion.</note> and which this performance call's us to, and ſo to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude. Let us be much in the thoughts and medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Gods goodneſſe to us, whether in our own <hi>particular</hi> perſons, in the mercies, which we have received <hi>there,</hi> or in the <hi>Generall</hi> ſtate of the <hi>City,</hi> in the mercies, which we have received in common, and together with <hi>that;</hi> Both of them are to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider'd by us, and both very ſutable to this work of <hi>our Publick Thanksgiving.</hi> Look as in a day of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick <hi>Humiliation,</hi> we are to be humbled, not only for <hi>Nationall,</hi> but for <hi>Perſonall ſins:</hi> So alſo in a day of <hi>Publick Thanksgiving,</hi> we are to remember not only our <hi>Nationall,</hi> but Perſonall <hi>mercies;</hi> eſpecially as our <hi>particular Perſons</hi> have any thing more <hi>ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>red</hi> in thoſe mercies as we have ſome of us done; In the recovery and continuance of our <hi>Healthe;</hi> In the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, and preſervation of our <hi>Eſtates;</hi> In the free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and deliverance from <hi>Enemies,</hi> or whatever elſe we can name, or think of. Look how far any doe more partake in <hi>mercy,</hi> ſo ſhould they more partake in <hi>Thanksgiving.</hi> The Obſervation of <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick</hi> mercies ſhould occaſion in us <hi>private</hi> Reflexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; And the reflecting upon <hi>private</hi> mercies, ſhould more <hi>quicken</hi> us in <hi>publick</hi> acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. But this is our great miſery, that we are for the moſt part but defective in <hi>either.</hi> We are ſo buſy commonly in the <hi>injoyment</hi> of mercies, that we have no <hi>leaſure</hi> to be <hi>thankefull</hi> for them. Though the Lord doth exceedingly abound in the manifeſtation of his Goodneſſe to us in all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, in our health, in our plenty, in our ſafety,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:99989:24"/>and miraculous preſervation: And above all in the continuance of his Goſpel, and Ordinances, and ſoule opportunities amongſt us; yet truly for the Generall we are very little ſenſible of them, or af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with them, or thankfull under them; even thoſe who if they ſhould looſe them, would ſooneſt <hi>miſſe</hi> them. What doe I ſpeak of <hi>Thankefullneſſe;</hi> when we have much adoe to keep our ſelves from <hi>murmuring</hi> and repining at Gods dealings with us. The Lord had never an heavier hand in his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtations with backſliding <hi>Iſrael,</hi> then he hath with many amongſt <hi>our ſelves.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Well, Let us here be ſeaſonably awakened from this preſent <hi>Occaſion</hi> before us, to lay theſe things more to <hi>Heart,</hi> then ever yet we have done. Oh it ſhould make us to love and ſerve this God ſo much the more, who ha's done ſo much for us; that ſo he may ſtill take pleaſure in us, and delight to dwell amongſt us for Good: To bleſſe us in our Perſons, in our imployments, in our eſtates, in our Families, and in all our Relations: And <hi>may defend this City to ſave it for his own ſake,</hi> and <hi>for his ſervant Davids ſake,</hi> that is, for his ſonne <hi>Jeſus Christs</hi> ſake to all following, and ſucceeding Generations even to the end of the world. <hi>Amen, Amen!</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
